I got this recipe for marinated portobello
mushroom steaks from Colleen Patrick-Goudreau's
30-Day Vegan Challenge book and I've actually
cut the recipe in half. But, you'll probably
want to double it since each person should
actually get 2 mushrooms.
You could use this marinade for vegetables
and mushrooms and grill them in the summer.
They'd be perfect on a wrap, in a salad or
even just by themselves. I can't wait to find
out what you guys do with this recipe. Let
me know in the comments!
I'm using 6 portobello mushrooms and removing
the gills. This is actually optional. Make
sure you remove the stems as well and wipe
the tops of the mushrooms.
In a bowl, combine ¼ cup balsamic vinegar,
¼ cup soy sauce, ¼ cup of water and ½ teaspoon
each of dried rosemary, dried thyme, and dried
oregano. You're gonna also need ⅛ teaspoon
of black pepper.
Whisk that all together and you're going to
pour it over your mushrooms and marinate thems
for at least 30 minutes.
After 30 minutes, heat some oil in a pan on
medium heat. Add as many mushrooms that will
fit in the pan with their tops down. Cook
them for about 3-5 minutes on each side, then
pour in some of the marinade.
Cover them and cook them for 10 minutes, and
make sure you just turn them halfway through.
Repeat this for the remaining mushrooms and
you're all done.
Portobello mushrooms have such a nice texture
and this marinade is awesome. You could do
so much with these mushrooms and the marinade.
Thanks for watching Vegan Cooking with Love!
If you liked this video, please give it a
thumbs up and share it with a friend. And
don't forget to subscribe so you get my new
videos. I'll see you next time!